Guide to the Potomac Area Council American Youth Hostels records, 1943-2011 MS2196
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Potomac Area Council American Youth Hostels records
1943-2011
1946-2005
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Messersmith, Donald
MS2196
16.25 Linear Feet
Collection includes correspondence, brochures, pamphlets, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, slides, scrapbooks, audio and video tapes, and cloth materials. The material dates from 1943-2011. The material in the collection covers the history of the Potomac Area Council of American Youth Hostels, especially the activities of its former Executive Director and board president, Don Messersmith.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Donald Messersmith in three accretions. One in 2005, another in 2008 and another in 2011.
Historical Note
Potomac Area Council American Youth Hostels (PAC-AYH) is an organization that promotes outdoor recreational activities and runs three youth hostels in Washington, Harper's Ferry, West Virginia, and Baltimore. It is affiliated with Hostelling International and Hostelling International USA (formerly American Youth Hostels (AYH)).
Justin Cline founded the Potomac Area Council in 1943 as an offshoot of the international hostelling movement. The organization's mission was to "develop healthy, self-reliant, well-informed, community-minded and world-minded citizens and to further good will among people of all lands." To accomplish this, the organization promoted inexpensive outdoor and social activities for people of all ages, such as dances, bicycling, and hiking. As a secondary function, it established low-cost accommodations for travelers engaged in these activities.
In its early years, the organization focused on providing recreational opportunities for the multitudes that swarmed to Washington during World War II. After the war ended, many of its members stayed in Washington and continued to organize recreational activities and establish hostels. In the early 1950s, it became active in promoting trails, including working with Supreme Court Justice William O. Douglas in the preservation of the Chesapeake and Ohio (C&O) Canal (see C&O Canal Association records, MS2027). PAC then established a now-defunct chain of hostels for hikers along the canal. It also ran a bicycle concession at Hains Point in East Potomac Park. During this time, the group was relatively small and centered on recreational activities for its members.
In the late 1960s, however, it began to reach out more to the surrounding community. Although PAC began bicycling programs for inner city youth in the early 1950s, it expanded them in the late 1960s and early 1970s. It would continue to promote bicycling through the 1980s, and continues to provide programs for inner city youth today.
An offshoot organization, the Boot & Sprocket Club, formed from some of the original hostellers after marriage and "settling down." The organization continues to hold reunions.
Today, running hostels is the main function of PAC. The organization has managed several hostels in the Washington area through its history. PAC's main hostel, as well as its headquarters, is currently located at 11th and K Streets, NW, in Washington.
PAC has published several newsletters and brochures, as well as hiking and bicycling guides.
Don Messersmith, a professor of Entomology and Ornithology at the University of Maryland, has been involved with PAC since 1950 and once served as its executive director and president of the board. As the donor, he is the most prominently featured individual in the collection.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection includes administrative files, correspondence, brochures, pamphlets, newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, slides, scrapbooks, audiotapes, and cloth materials. The material dates from 1943-2011. The material in the collection covers the history of the Potomac Area Council of American Youth Hostels, especially the activities of its former Executive Director and board president, Don Messersmith. He gathered much of the material for the celebration of the organization's fiftieth anniversary. There are also many slides from the late 1940s and early 1950s of hostel trips throughout the United States many local to Maryland, Virginia, West Virginia, and Pennsylvania. These slides appear to have been owned at one time by Edwinning Willmann. There are also annoted photograph albums that cover the same time period and appear to have images of the same or similar tripts. Many of these scrapbooks were owned by Donna Willmann.
The folders in boxes 4-7 are from a second accretion and are only partially processed. The material has been refoldered, but only organized in a general alphabetical sort by folder title. The materials in the folders and the folder titles are in the original order. There has been some photocopying of documents with mold damage and also the removal of rusty paperclips. The material in box 7 are from multiple series based on their material type.
Collection Organization
Organized into seven series: Administrative files, Newsletters and pamphlets, Graphics, Scrapbooks and annotated photograph albums, Audiotapes, Ephemera, and 2011 donation.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Chesapeake and Ohio Canal (Md. and Washington, D.C.); Black-and-white slides; Washington (D.C.); Scrapbooks; Photographs; Color slides; Hostels; Hostelling International-American Youth Hostels; Hostelling International; Hiking; Bicycling; Bird watching -- Europe; Bird watching; Audiotapes; Baltimore (Md.); Harpers Ferry (W. Va.); Washington Metropolitan Area; Douglas, William O. (William Orville); American Youth Hostels, inc.; Potomac Area Council American Youth Hostels; Shackleton, Polly; Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park (Agency: U.S.); Potomac Area Council of Hostelling International USA
- Administrative files, 1945-2011; Series 1; 3 Linear Feet (Box 1)
  Arrangement
  Arranged primiarily alphabetically.
  The folders in boxes 4-6, 12 are from a second accretion and are only partially processed. The material has been refoldered, but only organized in a general alphabetical sort by folder title. The materials in the folders and the folder titles are in the original order. There has been some photocopying of documents with mold damage and also the removal of rusty paperclips.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes correspondence, meeting minutes, agendas, executive reports, vision statements, membership applications, membership directories, and documents relating to PAC's 25th and 50th anniversary celebrations, as well as trips. The documents date from 1945 to 2011. A folder contains the documentation pertaining to a bird-watching trip to Europe that Messersmith led in 1966, including correspondence, budgets, and reports about the excursion.
  - Correspondence, 11/1950-12/30/2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, agendas, etc., 1955-11/24/1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
  - Executive reports & vision statements, 1970-12/13/1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership applications & manuals, 01/09/1974-08/16/1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Directories and membership lists, 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - PAC-AYH 25th anniversary celebration, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Organization history - 50th anniversary, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Trip information, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AYH bird study tour 1966, 1950-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Youth Hostel Inc., 1965-1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Youth Hostels, 1994-1996; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - AYH Newsletters, 1955-1959; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - AYH Eastern Region, 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - American Youth Hostel Council Personnel Resource List, 1971; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Baltimore International Youth Hostel (friends of, Original Group), 1981; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Baltimore International Youth Hostel proposed structure and projections, 1982; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Baltimore International Youth Hostel paperwork for 17 West Mulberry St. (org.), 1983; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Baltimore International Youth Hostel promotion, 1986-1987; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Baltimore Maryland Councl, 1956; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Phil Baker, 1962; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bicycle Center, 1948; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Clarksville, Maryland, 1946; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    General
    Application for Youth Hostel Charter
  - Come Hosteling and Youth Hostel News newsletters, 1948-1955; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Come Hosteling newsletters, 1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Comments of Sectretary Stewart L. Udall, 1963-1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Contacts Maryland, 1948-1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Councils: Washington DC Potomac Area Council, 1952-1953; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Current soundbites, 1950; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Donald H. Messersmith file, 1995-2011; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    See also Folder 20 Box 4
  - Hosteling International USA annual report, 2008; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    This file includes undated material
  - Hosteling International, USA, 2009-2011; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Hostels Maryland, 1954-1955; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Bill Johnson, 1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ed Kmosena, 1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Laurel Maryland, 1945-1948; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Media releases (hostel copy), 1984-1986; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Donald H. Messersmith, 1968; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Nalley Land Youth Hostel, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - newsletters and correspondence, 1987-1988; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Photos washington dc IYHF meeting, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Potomac Area Youth Hostels [1/2], 1949-1950; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Potomac Area Youth Hostels [2/2], 1949-1950; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Washington D.C. Potomac Area, 1955-1956, 1959; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes a newspaper clipping from the Washington Post about the C&O Canal
  - Potomac Council, 1960; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Potomac Area Council Board minutes, 1986; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Potomac Area Council correspondence [1/2], 1962-1964; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Potomac Area Council correspondence [2/2], 1962-1964; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Potomac Area correspondence, 1963; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Potomac Area Council minutes, 1965; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Potomac Area Council correspondence, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Potomac Area Council correspondence, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Potomac Area council correspondence, 1966-1969; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Potomac Area Council correspondence [1/2], 1966-1969; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Potomac Area Council correspondence [2/2], 1966-1969; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Potomac Area Council documents, 1969; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Potomac Area Council starting January 1970 [1/3], Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Potomac Area Council starting January 1970 [2/3], Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Potomac Area Council starting January 1970 [3/3], Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Potomac Area Council AYH, 1971; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Potomac Area Council AYH, 1972; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Potomac Area Council, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Potomac Area Washington DC, 1973; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Potomac Area Council Washington DC, 1974; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Potomac Area correspondence, 2007-2008; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Sykesville, Maryland, 1940; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Miriam Trikosko, 1965; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Virginia, 1947; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Washington International Youth Hostel: income & expense estimated for Whitehall, D.C., 1967; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Washington International Youth Hostel, 1967; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Washington International Youth Hostel, 1968-1971; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    clippings taken with Shirley (temple) Black
  - Washington International Youth Hostel, 1974; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Washington International Youth Hostel, 1968-1970; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Newsletters and pamphlets, 1946-2005; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes national AYH newsletters, PAC newsletters, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and brochures produced by or relating to PAC. The documents date from 1946 to 2005. The series contains most issues of PAC's newsletters, called "Come Hosteling," then "Volunteer Action," then "Tall Tales Tattler," then "Voyager." These newsletters cover some of PAC's activities. They also include articles on PAC's involvement with Supreme Court Justice William O. Douglas and the C&O Canal Association and with D.C. Councilwoman Polly Shackleton's campaign for bicycle trails in Washington (see Polly Shackleton, papers, MS2031).
  - Hostel Manager Communique, 1987-1988; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 07/1946-07/1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 02/1953-01/1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 02/1959-12/1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 01/1964-12/1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 01/1969-12/1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 01/1975-12/1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 01/1981-12/1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 01/1984-12/1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Potomac Area Council "Come Hosteling", 01/1989-12/1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Potomac Area Council "Volunteer Action" & "Tall Tales Tattler", 10/1994-09/1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Potomac Area Council "Voyager", 12/1999-02/2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Potomac Area Council "Voyager", 2003-2010; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - National AYH newsletters, 1997-2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pamphlets, 1950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pamphlets, 1972-2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pamphlets, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1961-2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Graphics, 1943-2005; Series 3; 1.5 Linear Feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  Organized into two subseries: photographs and slides.
  This series includes photographs and slides of hostel trips. The photos and slides date from 1943 to 2005.
  - Photographs, Series 3 Subseries 1; 0.5 Linear Feet
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries contains photographs of hostel trips and events.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Photographs: "PAC-AYH 50 Years", 1943-1993; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Contains 14 photographs
    - Photographs: PAC 50th Anniversary Celebration: Recreation & Travel Display, 1943-1993; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Contains 20 photographs
    - Photographs, 1951-2005; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Contains 11 photographs
    - Dedication of Sandy Hook, 1962 May 2; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Flat box 7, Object 1)
    - Photographs, undated; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Contains 7 photographs
    - Photographs: "'From Cress' - B&S - AYH", undated; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Contains 61 photographs
    - Photographs: from Harold Wennberg to Don Messersmith, undated; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Contains 4 photographs
    - Oversize photographs, undated; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Contains 2 photographs
    - oversize photographs, undated; Series 3 Subseries 1 (Flat box 7, Oversize-folder 1)
      three black and white images. 1. Japanese hostelers visiting Seneca.. Caption reads "Japanese Hostelers visit Seneca, MD. Hostel as part of the "summer in America" program. AYH-ER on the right is Julian Bloch."
      2. Loretta Young, Actree promoted D.C. Hostel
      3. "National AYH leaders training course session - 1963- under the guidance of William A. Nelson, National Field Director (top row, far left)
  - Slides, 1947-1971; 1947-1958; Series 3 Subseries 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains slides primarily of hostel trips. The trips include many areas of North America and also Europe. The slides are dated from
    - New England trip, 1947 July 3; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - AYH Hostels, 1947 July 26 - 1949 July 12; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Trip locations included: Aldie Va and Herald Harbor.
    - Delaware Water Gap, Fredericksburg, Annapolis, Tangier Island and baby Johnny jr., 1948 May - November; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Port Tobacco, Greenwood, Blair Park, Thurmont, Charles County, Wolf Rock, 1948-1950; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Parade [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1949 January; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - General Youth Europe trip, 1949 June 6 - 1949 July 4; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Canada [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1949 July; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - AYH trip to Canada [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1949 July; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - New York City, Lancaster, Manada Gap, PA, Cacapon State Park, WV [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1949; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - General Youth Hostel [1/3], 1949 July - 1952 July; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Trip locations include: Aldie, Mt. Washington NH, New England, Champion, Pa., Port Tobacco, Washington, DC, Old Rag, Davis, WV., Bel Air, Md., Laurel Fork, WV, Thurmont, Md., Anapolis, Md., Greenwood--Olney Theatre, Herald Harbor, and Westminster.
    - General Youth Hostel [2/3], 1949 July - 1952 July; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Trip locations include: Port Tobacco, Greenwood, Yorktown, Pa., Nags Head, NC, Prince Frederick, Md., Leesburg, Va., Waterford, Va., Harper's Ferry, Denton, Md., Champion, Pa., Lake Champlain, Aldie, Va.
      There are also pictures of a cycle trip reunion.
    - General Youth Hostel [3/3], 1949 July - 1952 July; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Trip locations include: Old Rag, Bel Air, Md., Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket, Davis WV, Appalachian Trail, Gray Rock Inn, Elk Neck State Park, Cave Mountain Lake, Pine Grove, Rock Creek, Fort Valley, Gettysburg, Circleville, Va., Skyline Drive, Smokeys, Thurmont, Md., Caledonia Park, Pa., Aldie
    - "Betty McConnell & Sam Cress - Early Potomac AYH", 11/1948-09/1967; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Contains 17 slides
    - Leesburg (1951), Aldie, Quaker Farm, Washington, DC, Cape May, Port Tobacco, Circleville VA, Caldonia, PA, Thurmont [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1951, undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified slides, 04/1954-10/1958; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Contains 108 slides
    - AYH History, 06/1954-05/1993; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Contains 78 slides
    - Env. Educ., 04/1954-05/1990; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Contains 32 slides
    - White Mountains [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1956 October; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - White Mountains [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1956 October; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Niagra Falls [Edwinnie Willmann slides], 1957 July 4; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified slides, 1958-1993; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified slides, 06/1968-06/1971; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Contains 16 slides
    - Barton [or Barker] in Virginia [Edwinnie Willmann slides], undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Climbing rocks [Edwinnie Willmann slides], undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Sherando Lake, DE [Edwinnie Willmann slides], undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Ski trips: Canada, Vermont, Davis, VA, Beach trip, Rock climbers, Blackwater Falls Ski Slope, undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Youth Hostel trips [1/2], undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Trip locations include: Williamsburg, Jamestown, Yorktown, Pa., Aldie and Waterford, Charlottesville, Manito, Nags Head, Lake Champlain, Lake George, Glen Falls, Hudson River, Saratoga Springs.
    - Youth Hostel trips [2/2], undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Trip locations include: Lake Champlain, Jamestown, Champion, Pa., Washington, DC (Cherryblossoms).
    - loose slides, undated; Series 3 Subseries 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      These slides were loose in a box. They were reordered to be grouped with slides of the same trip.
      Trip locations include: Difficult Run, Winchester, Lincoln, NB, Franklin, Shadyside, Aldie, Pennifield Locks, Greenwood, Chop, Detroit, Champion, Pa., Gettysburg, Pa., Midwest (Amana Iowa, Kentucky, Virginia, West Virginia), New York, Appalachian Trail, Swallow Falls, Md., Skyline Drive.
      There are also images of people: Betty and Eddie, Edwinnine, Donna, and Jim.
- Scrapbooks and annotated photograph albums, 1940 ca.-1995; Series 4; 1.5 Linear Feet (Box 2, Box 3)
  This series contains scrapbooks and annotated photograph albums, as well as exhibit displays for the fiftieth anniversary of PAC. The scrapbooks relate to the fiftieth anniversary of Potomac Area Council. Also included in this series are two printed books that serve as scrapbooks. The photograph albums are all related to hostel trips. Some of these trips are also represented in the slides that are part of series 3 subseries 2. The dates of the material ranges from the 1940s through 1995.
  - Betty Cress, 1940 ca. -1959 ca.; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Early Years: Boot 'N' Sprocket Club, 1940 ca. -1959 ca.; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Potomac Area Council American Youth Hostels Memory Book: The First Fifty Years, 1943-1993; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - PAC-AYH 50 Years, 1943-1993; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified pages, 1945-1950; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Donna's Hostel trip [1/2] [Donna Willmann album], 1946-1947; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Donna's Hostel trip [2/2] [Donna Willmann album], 1946-1947; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Various trips vol. 1, 1946 May - 1947 April; Series 4 (Box 13, Volume 4)
  - Various trips vol. 2, 1947 April - 1947 August; Series 4 (Box 13, Volume 5)
  - Camping / biking trip Vol. 3 [Donna Willmann album] [1/2], 1947 August - 1948 February; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Camping / biking trip Vol. 3 [Donna Willmann album] [2/2], 1947 August - 1948 February; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - New England trip vol. 1, 1947; Series 4 (Box 13, Volume 1)
  - New England trip vol. 2, 1947; Series 4 (Box 13, Volume 2)
  - New England trip vo. 3, 1947; Series 4 (Box 13, Volume 3)
  - Trips Vol. 4 [Donna Willmann album] [1/2], 1948 May - 1948 June; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Trips Vol. 4 [Donna Willmann album] [2/2], 1948 May - 1948 June; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Lake Champlain Bicycle Trip, 1948; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lake Champlain [Donna Willmann album], 1948; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Europe trip [Donna Willmann album], 1949; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Trips to Virginia, Kentucky, Washington DC, and Alaska [Donna Willmann album], 1955-1964; Series 4 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Various trips [1/2], Circa 1985; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Various trips [2/2], Circa 1985; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - To and from Phillips Mt. Campus [1/2], 1987; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - To and from Phillips Mt. Campus [2/2], 1987; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 50th anniversary displays [1/2], 1995 ca.; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 6)